

Gokul Hariharan, Ph.D.

Ames, IA. | gokulhariharan1991@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/gokulhariharan/

Summary

I have rich experience encompassing fluid mechanics, linear and nonlinear systems theory, multiphase flows, control theory, matrix theory, distributed systems analysis, computational fluid dynamics (CFD), discrete element modeling (DEM), principal component analysis (PCA), model reduction, and artificial neural networks (ANN). I am proficient in finite element, finite volume, finite difference, and spectral methods.

Experience



Research Assistant

Iowa State University
Runtime verification for safety critical systems.

Jan 2021 - Present (2 months +)



Postdoctoral Researcher

University of Southern California

Apr 2020 – Dec 2020 (9 months)



Research Assistant

University of Minnesota

Jan 2016 - Apr 2020 (4 years 4 months)

- ~ Steered linear nonmodal analysis in viscoelastic channel flow using well-conditioned spectral methods.
- ~ Carried out direct numerical simulations by creating codes in C++.
- ~ Identified the most sensitive location to potentially trigger elastic turbulence.



Teaching Assistant

University of Minnesota Jan 2019 - May 2019 (5 months), Sep 2018 - Dec 2018 (4 months) Held discussions and proctored exams for two graduate-level courses, Linear Algebra and Fluid Mechanics.



Research Assistant

Indian Institute of Technology, Delhi

Jan 2014 - Jun 2015 (1 year 6 months)

- ~ Simulated the influence of smaller (ash) particles on larger (coal) particles during fluidization by using Discrete Element Modeling (DEM).
- ~ Tracked coal and ash movements through methods similar to Molecular Dynamics Simulations (MDS).
- ~ Leveraged Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD) to simulate the gas used to fluidize coal..
- ~ Won the best poster award for presenting a poster in Open House 2015 in IIT Delhi.



Research Intern

BITS Pilani, Hyderabad Campus

May 2011 - Jun 2011 (2 months)

- ~ Identified an optimal solution between two conflicting objectives in job scheduling in the semiconductor industry by using Artificial Neural Networks (ANN).
- ~ Used ANN to predict flow stress in the dynamic strain aging regime of austenitic stainless steel 316.

Education

Iowa State University

Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.), Computer Science

2021 - 2023



University of Minnesota

Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.), Chemical Engineering | GPA: 3.5.

2015 - 2020

My specialization is in Fluid Mechanics. The dissertation consists of four projects:

-- Amplification of localized body forces in viscoelastic channel flows

Analyzed external disturbances in the form of localized point forces (impulses) in viscoelastic channel flow.

- -- Well-conditioned spectral methods for nonmodal analysis of Newtonian and viscoelastic channel flows Employed recently reported well-conditioned spectral methods to analyze the response of a 2D viscoelastic channel flow to small-amplitude sinusoidal disturbances.
- -- Stress amplification in inertialess viscoelastic channel flows

Identified huge, near-wall stress gradients in plane Poiseuille flow and near-center stress gradients in plane Couette flow; a potential root-cause for low-inertia instabilities in viscoelastic channel flows.

-- Direct numerical simulations (DNS) using well-conditioned methods

Provided a new method to perform DNS using well-conditioned spectral methods.



Indian Institute of Technology, Delhi

Master of Technology (M.Tech.), Chemical Engineering | GPA: 3.8

2013 - 2015



National Institute of Technology Warangal

Bachelor of Technology (B.Tech.), Chemical Engineering | GPA: 3.8

2009 - 2013

Honors & Awards

F Wendell Miller Scholarship – Department of Computer Science, Iowa State University, Jan 2021

CEMS Outstanding TA Award - CEMS, University of Minnesota, Jun 2019

Sebastian C. Reyes Fellowship - CEMS, University of Minnesota Jan 2016

Stephan J. Salter Fellowship - CEMS, University of Minnesota Jan 2016

Certificate of Excellence - Chemical Engineering Society, IIT Delhi, 2015 Department rank 1 (of 25)

Best Research Poster Award, Open House 2015 - Indian Institute of Technology Delhi 2015

Roll of Honor Gold Medal - National Institute of Technology Warangal, 2013, Department rank 1 (of 100)

Skills

C++ (Expert, 7 years' experience) • Qt • MATLAB • Python • Mathematica • MS Office • Git • OpenMP • MPI • ANN • Research • Finite Element Method • Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD) • Decision-Making • Creative Problem Solving • Project Management • Attention to Detail • Scientific Writing • Model Predictive Control • Linear Analysis • Nonlinear Analysis • Applied Mathematics • Modeling and Simulation • Parallel programing • Thermal Engineering • Teaching

Papers and Presentations

Please visit https://gokulhari.github.io/webpage/Papers.html